A Guide to the Persinger and Staples Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #1000
Persinger and Staples Family Papers 1793-1937 Inclusive
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
Collection number 1000
300 items
Collector: Mrs. David W. Persinger
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection (# 1000 ) was purchased by the Library from Mrs. David W. Persinger of Virginia Beach, Virginia, ca. 1940.
Scope and Content
This collection contains ca. 300 items, 1793-1937, consisting of personal correspondence, financial papers, legal papers, and bound volumes, pertaining to the Persinger Family and Staples Family of Virginia.
The personal correspondence concern various events relating to the lives of both the Persinger Family and Staples Family. The letters are divided into three groups: "Letters between Daniel de Jarnette Staples and Mary (Waugh) Staples"; "Letters between David W. Persinger and his mother, Mrs. M. E. Martin"; and, "Correspondence of Persinger Family and Staples Families." The letters between Daniel Staples and Mary Staples are written during the period of 1879-1897, with the dominant theme being their enduring love for one another and the elaborate preparations that are undertaken for their 1880 wedding. The letters between David W. Persinger and his mother occur during the period of 1893-1896 and are primarily focused on David Persinger's educational life in regards to his grades and his progress at the University of Virginia. Correspondence, 1894-1937, between the Persinger and Staples families cover a variety of topics including the various ailments of Daniel Staples' invalid uncle, Judge Waller Redd Staples, and business related information concerning the Staples Family.
"The Autobiography of Judge Samuel G. Staples" elaborates the educational life of Judge Staples and his appointment to a judgeship in Richmond, Virginia. Judge Samuel G. Staples attended Randolph Macon Academy and the University of Virginia Law School.
The financial papers, 1891-1908, concern David Staples and Mary Staples. Items include a bankbook of Mary W. Staples, various receipts from merchants, city and state tax return vouchers and demands for payment of goods and services by David Staples. Also included is a list, n.d., of slaves and prices for Judge [Samuel G.] Staples.
The legal papers, 1892-1903, are composed of deeds and insurance policies. The contracts include agreements between David Staples and others, a notary public notice, and a notice from an investment firm. The deeds include agreements between either David Staples or Mary Staples and other parties. There is a deed, January 18, 1896, between the Old Dominion Building and Loan Association of Richmond, Virginia and Mary W. Staples. In addition, there are different types of insurance policies taken out by David Staples or Mary Staples, including fire insurance and life insurance, with the majority of them pertaining to those ensuring against fire.
The remaining items in the collection are bound volumes which include day books, 1856-1887, kept by Samuel G. Staples; and, program books, 1902-1910 and 1905-1912, in which are play programs. Among the day books is one kept by Samuel G. Staples and Waller Redd Staples as executors of the estate of Abram Penn Staples.
Container List
- Correspondence
  - 1879-1880Letters between Daniel de Jarnette Staples and Mary (Waugh) Staples, (3 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - 1890-1897, n.d.Letters between Daniel de Jarnette Staples and Mary (Waugh) Staples, (3 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - 1893-1896Letters between David W. Persinger and his mother, Mrs. M. E. Martin (Box Box 1)
  - 1894-1937, n.d.Correspondence of the Persinger Family and the Staples Family (Box Box 1)
- Topical
  - 1879Autobiography of Judge Samuel G. Staples (Box Box 2)
  - 1891-1908, n.d.Financial Papers, (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - 1892-1896Legal Papers: Contracts (Box Box 2)
  - 1892-1897Legal Papers: Deeds (Box Box 2)
  - 1892-1903Legal Papers: Insurance Policies (Box Box 2)
  - 1895,1924,n.d.Miscellaneous Papers (Box Box 2)
  - 1902-1910, n.d.Programs (removed from the "Program Book") (Box Box 2)
  Bound Volumes
- Bound Volumes
  - 1856-1862"Day Book"- kept by Samuel G. Staples (Box Box 2)
  - 1872-1887"Day Book"- kept by Samuel G. Staples (Box Box 2)
  - 1878-1883"Day Book"- kept by Samuel G. Staples (Box Box 3)
  - n.d."Day Book"- kept by Samuel G. Staples (Box Box 3)
  - 1902-1910"Program Book"- kept by Samuel G. Staples (Box Box 3)
  - 1905-1912"Program Book"- kept by Samuel G. Staples (Box Box 3)